A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - George L. Hinman, Series J.2 FA346
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Politics - George L. Hinman, Series J.2
1959-1970
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Hinman, George
FA346
98 Document Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson Aldrich Rockefeller was born on July 8, 1908, in Bar Harbor, Maine, the third child of John Davison Rockefeller, Jr., and Abby Aldrich Rockefeller. He graduated from the Lincoln School of Teachers College at Columbia University in New York City in 1926. Mr. Rockefeller attended Dartmouth College where he was elected to Phi Beta Kappa, graduating cum laude in 1930 with an A.B. degree in economics.
After college, Mr. Rockefeller was active in family enterprises, including real estate, banking, and family philanthropies. His major business interests in time became focused on Rockefeller Center and Latin America. In 1938, he became the president of Rockefeller Center.
In 1935, because of his interest in national affairs and his desire to learn about U.S. business abroad, Mr. Rockefeller became a director of Creole Petroleum Company, the Venezuelan subsidiary of Standard Oil of New Jersey. This association led eventually to his deep, life-long interest in Latin America. He made extensive visits to Latin America in 1937 and 1939 to study economic, social, and political conditions. He resigned his directorship in the Creole Petroleum Company in 1940.
In 1940, Mr. Rockefeller and his four brothers organized the Rockefeller Brothers Fund to carry out a broad range of philanthropic activities.
Throughout his life Mr. Rockefeller was an avid supporter of the arts. He served as a trustee, treasurer, president, and chair of the board of the Museum of Modern Art, which was cofounded by his mother. In 1954, he founded the Museum of Primitive Art, which collected of indigenous art of the Americas, Africa, Oceania, and early Asia and Europe.
After his 1939 visit to Latin America, Mr. Rockefeller prepared a memorandum for President Franklin D. Roosevelt outlining his deep concern over Nazi influence and penetration into that part of the world. In the memo he recommended a U.S. program of cooperation with the nations of the western hemisphere to achieve better relations among these nations and to help raise their standards of living. Largely as a result of this memo, President Roosevelt asked Mr. Rockefeller in August of 1940 to initiate and head a new program ultimately known as the Office of Inter-American Affairs. Mr. Rockefeller served as Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs, his first full-time position in public service.
Mr. Rockefeller served in this position until December 1944, when President Roosevelt appointed him Assistant Secretary of State for American Republic Affairs. In this post, Mr. Rockefeller initiated the Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace in Mexico City in February of 1945. It resulted in the Act of Chapultepec, which provided the framework for economic, social, and defense cooperation among the nations of the western hemisphere and set the principle that an attack on one of these nations would be regarded as an attack on all and jointly resisted.
Mr. Rockefeller signed the Act of Chapultepec on behalf of the United States. He also attended the United Nations Conference on International Organization in San Francisco in 1945. At the conference, there was considerable opposition to the idea of permitting, within the UN Charter, the formation of regional pacts such as the Act of Chapultepec. Mr. Rockefeller, who believed that the inclusion was essential, especially to U.S. policy in Latin America, successfully argued the need for regional pacts within the framework of the United Nations. The importance of this victory was underscored by the subsequent formation of NATO, SEATO, and the Rio Pact.
During these war-time years, Mr. Rockefeller also served as Chairman of the Inter-American Development Commission, which was established in June 1940 to reorganize and revitalize Latin American economies following the loss of European markets. He was also the U.S. Co-Chairman of the Mexican-American Development Commission to help Mexico emerge as an industrial nation in the transition from war to peace.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Assistant Secretary of State on August 24, 1945.
Upon his return to private life in New York in 1946, Mr. Rockefeller became chair of the board of Rockefeller Center and undertook a program of physical expansion. Two other initiatives during this period illustrate Mr. Rockefeller's continuing interest in Latin America and international economic development. In July of 1946, the Rockefeller brothers established a philanthropic organization, the American International Association for Economic and Social Development (AIA). AIA financed nonprofit projects to ameliorate health, educational, agricultural, and other social problems in the poorer areas of Latin America. Nelson Rockefeller served as President from July 1946 to June 1953 and from January 1957 to December 1958. In 1947, he organized the International Basic Economy Corporation (IBEC), a business corporation to help raise living standards in foreign countries through new economic enterprises. In its early years, IBEC concentrated on enterprises in Latin America but later expanded its activities to other regions. Mr. Rockefeller served as IBEC President from January 1947 to June 1953 and from January 1956 to December 1958.
In his inaugural address in January 1949, President Harry S. Truman announced the Point IV program for providing technical assistance to developing nations. This concept was based in part on programs Mr. Rockefeller and his associates had developed through the Office of the Coordinator of Inter-American Affairs and the private, philanthropic AIA. In November of 1950, President Truman asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the International Development Advisory Board. The Board was charged with recommending policies for carrying out the Point IV program. The Board's report, entitled "Partners in Progress," provided the basic blueprint for America's foreign assistance program.
On November 20, 1952, President-elect Dwight D. Eisenhower asked Mr. Rockefeller to serve as Chairman of the President's Advisory Committee on Government Organization, a group created to recommend ways to improve the efficiency of the executive branch of the government. As Chairman of that committee, Mr. Rockefeller recommended 13 reorganization plans to the President, 10 of which were approved by Congress. These plans achieved basic changes in the organization of the Department of Defense, the Department of Agriculture, and the Office of Defense Mobilization, among others. Another of the plans led to the establishment of the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. In June 1953, Mr. Rockefeller was appointed Under Secretary of the new department. He was especially active in the department's legislative program, recommending measures that covered an additional ten million people under the Social Security program. He resigned as HEW Under Secretary in 1954 to become Special Assistant to the President for Foreign Affairs.
While serving as Special Assistant, Mr. Rockefeller played a key role in the development of the "Open Skies" proposal for checking on world armaments through mutual air reconnaissance. He accompanied President Eisenhower to the Geneva Summit Conference in 1955, where the plan was proposed to the world by the President. Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Special Assistant on December 31, 1955.
Mr. Rockefeller first ran for public office in 1958 and was elected Governor of New York on November 4, defeating incumbent Averill Harriman. He took office January 1, 1959, and was subsequently re-elected Governor three more times, thus becoming the first Governor in the nation's history to be elected to four 4-year terms.
Nelson Rockefeller's tenure as a public servant in the federal government was a formative period in his life. By the time he left Washington to assume the governorship of New York, he had received a thorough education in the workings of the federal government. His chairmanship of PACGO permitted him to examine every aspect of the executive branch. This and his work in HEW exposed him to a wide variety of domestic issues. He gained experience in initiating legislation, in foreign policy and diplomacy, in domestic and international economics, and in national security and military affairs. In the process he also received an education in national politics and gained a reputation for being an effective and hardworking administrator. Most importantly, these appointments provided him with the opportunity to form the friendships and personal associations that served him throughout his political career.
Mr. Rockefeller resigned as Governor of New York in December 1973. In August 1974, President Gerald R. Ford nominated him to fill the vacant vice presidency following the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon. Mr. Rockefeller served as Vice President from December 19, 1974, to January 20, 1977. Nelson Rockefeller died on January 26, 1979, in New York City.
Biographical/Historical note
George Lyon Hinman was born in Binghamton, New York. He graduated from Princeton University in 1927 and received a law degree from Harvard University in 1930. That same year he joined the law firm of Hinman, Howard & Kattell. He became partner and at one time headed the firm, with which he was still associated at that time of his death in 1997. Throughout his life, Hinman served on a variety of boards, including the New York State Board of Regents, Colgate University, and IBM.
Hinman first came to Nelson A. Rockefeller's attention in 1956, when he was named as counsel to the Temporary State Commission to Prepare for a Constitutional Convention, which was chaired by Rockefeller. Two years later, after Rockefeller was elected Governor, Hinman became his executive assistant. From 1960 to 1977, Hinman held the title of special counsel, Rockefeller Family and Associates.
George Hinman was an important aide during Rockefeller's four terms as governor, from 1959 to 1973, as well as throughout Rockefeller's tenure as Vice President under President Gerald Ford, from 1974 to 1977. Hinman also assisted Rockefeller in his unsuccessful campaigns for the Republican Presidential nomination in 1960, 1964, and 1968.
Politically, Hinman served on the Republican National Committee from 1959 to 1977, often as a member of the executive committee. He also served as Delegate-at-Large from New York State to the Republican conventions of 1960, 1964, and 1976. Following the inauguration of Jimmy Carter in 1977, Hinman resigned from the national committee, yet remained one of Rockefeller's advisors after his withdrawal from politics.
(Information from New York Times obituary)
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 04 J.2
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into 5 subseries:
Subseries 1 - General Correspondence, 1960-1970 Subseries 2 - State Files and Summaries, 1960-1970 Subseries 3 - Talent File, 1960-1970 Subseries 4 - Memos, 1959-1970 Subseries 5 - Correspondence, 1960-1968
Related Archival Materials note
Issues of the "Congressional Quarterly" from 1962-1971 are also available. Complete yearly runs exist for 1964-1967. Some issues were annotated by Mr. Hinman. A list of the issues is available at the Rockefeller Archive Center.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller papers, Activities (FA338)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, AIA-IBEC (FA339)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Art (FA340)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Countries (FA341)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, DNA (FA342)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Family and Friends (FA343)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Oral Histories (FA344)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - New York City Office (FA345)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Politics - Oscar M. Ruebhausen (FA347)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Projects (FA348)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential (FA349)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Washington, DC (FA350)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Ann C. Whitman - Politics (FA351)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Papers, Hugh Morrow Interviews (FA352)
Scope and Contents
This series contains the office files of George L. Hinman. They document official activities in the execution of his duties as a member of Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Public health -- Latin America; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Political campaigns -- United States; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); Philanthropy -- United States; State governments -- United States; Social problems -- Latin America; Venezuela; United States; Business; Business enterprises, Foreign; Civic improvement; Civics; Agriculture -- Latin America; Philanthropy; Art, Primitive; Arts; Brazil; National security -- United States; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Developing countries; Economic policy; Economics; Education; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; International economic relations; International relations; International relations -- United States; Latin America; Agriculture; Education -- Latin America; Federal government -- United States; Government agencies; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
- General Correspondence, 1960-1970; 1; 28.4 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged alphabetically by name or topic.
  Scope and Contents note
  These files contain correspondence from George Hinman to individuals on political matters that concerned Republican party politics and Governor Rockefeller's role within the party. The majority of the letters are from Hinman himself, although a significant number of letters were forwarded by another member of the Governor's staff to Hinman for acknowledgement. In these cases, the correspondence includes the copy of the letter signed by Governor Rockefeller.
  Many of the files include Hinman's "memorandum for files," which are his notations on individuals, telephone conversations with political operatives, or meetings or discussions with the individual. Many prominent political individuals are represented here, including U.S. Senator and 1964 Republican presidential candidate Barry Goldwater, New York Mayor John Lindsay, President Richard Nixon, Michigan Governor George Romney, and Pennsylvania Governor William Scranton.
  - Aagre - Adams (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams - Agree (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Agriculture (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Ahern - Albright (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alcorn - Allen (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Allett - American (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ames - Anderson (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Anderson - Appling (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Aragon - Arn (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Arnold - Association (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Atkinson - Azar (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - A General (Box 2, Folder 0011A)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - Babcock - Baker (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Baldridge - Barlow (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Barnard - Bartle (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bartlett - Baumhardt (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Baumhart - Bechtol (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Bechtold - Belcher (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Belfatto - Belin (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Bell - Bennett (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Benoit - Betts (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Bick - Birch (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Birch - Bliss (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Bliss, Ray C. (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Bliss, Ray C. (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Bliss, Ray C. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Bliss, Ray C. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Bliss - Bolack (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Boland - Borders (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Borella, Victor (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Borg - Bradley (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Bradshaw, Lester (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Brady - Brinkley (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Brinton, William (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Brinton, William (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Bristol - Brotzman (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Brown, Clarence - Brown, Ralph (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Brown, Robert - Brydges (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - Bocalo - Burbank (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Burch, Dean (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Burden - Burton (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Buschmann - Byrnes (Box 8, Folder 41)
  - B General (Box 8, Folder 0041A)
  - Cabitor - Cannam (Box 8, Folder 42)
  - Cannon - Carpenter (Box 8, Folder 43)
  - Carpentier - Chamberlain (Box 9, Folder 44)
  - Champion - Chapin (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Chapman, Bruce (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Chapman, Bruce (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Chapman - Cherney (Box 9, Folder 48)
  - Chernin, Bernard (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Cherry - Citrino (Box 10, Folder 50)
  - Civil Rights (Box 10, Folder 51)
  - Civil Rights (Box 10, Folder 52)
  - Claggert - Clarke, Garvey, E. (Box 10, Folder 53)
  - Clarke, Thurmond (Box 10, Folder 54)
  - Clarke, William - Cogswell (Box 10, Folder 55)
  - Cohen - Combe (Box 10, Folder 56)
  - Combs - Concannon (Box 11, Folder 57)
  - Conference Memos (Box 11, Folder 58)
  - Conference - Conte (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - Convention - Converse (Box 11, Folder 60)
  - Conway - Corbett (Box 11, Folder 61)
  - Corbin - Cotton (Box 11, Folder 62)
  - Cottrell - Covey (Box 12, Folder 63)
  - Cowen - Crane (Box 12, Folder 64)
  - Cranston - Craven (Box 12, Folder 65)
  - Crawford - Cundiff (Box 12, Folder 66)
  - Cunningham - Cybard (Box 12, Folder 67)
  - C General (Box 12, Folder 0067A)
  - Dabney - Davie (Box 13, Folder 68)
  - Davies, Aled P. (Box 13, Folder 69)
  - Davies, Dean (Box 13, Folder 70)
  - Deardourff - Delaney (Box 13, Folder 71)
  - de la Fontaine - D'Ewart (Box 13, Folder 72)
  - Dewey - Dineen (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - Diorio - Donner (Box 14, Folder 74)
  - Donohue - Donovan (Box 14, Folder 75)
  - Dooley - Douglass, Edward R. (Box 14, Folder 76)
  - Douglass, Robert R. (Box 14, Folder 77)
  - Douglass, Robert R. (Box 14, Folder 78)
  - Dove - Dudley (Box 14, Folder 79)
  - Duffy - DuPont (Box 15, Folder 80)
  - Duque - Dysinger (Box 15, Folder 81)
  - D General (Box 15, Folder 0081A)
  - Eadens - Edmundson (Box 15, Folder 82)
  - Education - Eisenhower College (Box 15, Folder 83)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 15, Folder 84)
  - Eisenhower, Edgar - Eldridge (Box 15, Folder 85)
  - Elections, 1960-1962 (Box 15, Folder 86)
  - Elections, 1960-1962 (Box 15, Folder 87)
  - Elfstrom - Ellsworth (Box 16, Folder 88)
  - Elston - Erby (Box 16, Folder 89)
  - Eroman - Eyssel (Box 16, Folder 90)
  - E General (Box 16, Folder 0090A)
  - Facts - Faunce (Box 16, Folder 91)
  - Fay - Fenner (Box 16, Folder 92)
  - Fensterer - Filosa (Box 17, Folder 93)
  - Filsinger - Fisher (Box 17, Folder 94)
  - Fitchett - Floyd (Box 17, Folder 95)
  - Flug - Ford (Box 17, Folder 96)
  - Foreign Countries, Africa - West Indies (Box 17, Folder 97)
  - Foreman - Fraser (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - Frayn, R. Mort (Box 18, Folder 99)
  - Frayn, R. Mort (Box 18, Folder 100)
  - Frayn, R. Mort (Box 18, Folder 101)
  - Frayn, R. Mort (Box 18, Folder 102)
  - Frazer - Fry (Box 18, Folder 103)
  - Fulkerson - Funston (Box 18, Folder 104)
  - Furness - Fyles (Box 18, Folder 105)
  - F General (Box 18, Folder 0105A)
  - Gabby - Galmayer (Box 19, Folder 106)
  - Galton - Gary (Box 19, Folder 107)
  - Gaskin - Gaynor (Box 19, Folder 108)
  - Gebhard - Geyer (Box 19, Folder 109)
  - Gibbs - Gillespie (Box 19, Folder 110)
  - Gillette - Gillies (Box 19, Folder 111)
  - Gilman - Glavin (Box 19, Folder 112)
  - Gleason - Goldstein (Box 20, Folder 113)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 114)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 115)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 116)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 117)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 118)
  - Goldwater, Barry (Box 20, Folder 119)
  - Goldwater Campaign (Box 21, Folder 120)
  - Goldwater Campaign (Box 21, Folder 121)
  - Goldwater Campaign (Box 21, Folder 122)
  - Goldsworthy - Goodwin (Box 21, Folder 123)
  - Gordon - Goushe (Box 21, Folder 124)
  - Governor's Conference (Box 21, Folder 125)
  - Gow - Grayson (Box 22, Folder 126)
  - Greeley - Griffen (Box 22, Folder 127)
  - Griffen - Grigsby (Box 22, Folder 128)
  - Grimes - Guest (Box 22, Folder 129)
  - Gulley - Gwinn (Box 22, Folder 130)
  - G General (Box 22, Folder 0130A)
  - Haas - Hall, James (Box 23, Folder 131)
  - Hall, Lawrence - Halvorsen (Box 23, Folder 132)
  - Ham - Hanes (Box 23, Folder 133)
  - Hanin - Harnish (Box 23, Folder 134)
  - Harper - Harris, John (Box 23, Folder 135)
  - Harris, M. H. - Hatchet (Box 23, Folder 136)
  - Hatfield, Mark (Box 24, Folder 137)
  - Hathaway - Hazelton (Box 24, Folder 138)
  - Healy - Helping (Box 24, Folder 139)
  - Henderson - Herlihy (Box 24, Folder 140)
  - Herman - Hermann (Box 24, Folder 141)
  - Hernandez - Hill (Box 24, Folder 142)
  - Hill, Herbert (Box 25, Folder 143)
  - Hill, Herbert (Box 25, Folder 144)
  - Hill, Herman - Hilibrand (Box 25, Folder 145)
  - Hillings - Hitesman (Box 25, Folder 146)
  - Hitt - Hogan (Box 25, Folder 147)
  - Hoke - Honeywell (Box 25, Folder 148)
  - Honig - Houghton (Box 26, Folder 149)
  - House - Howard, Edward (Box 26, Folder 150)
  - Howard, Ernest - Hubbs (Box 26, Folder 151)
  - Huckson - Humphrey (Box 26, Folder 152)
  - Humphreys, Ray (Box 26, Folder 153)
  - Humphreys, Ray (Box 26, Folder 154)
  - Hunter - Hyzer (Box 27, Folder 155)
  - H General (Box 27, Folder 0155A)
  - Iannone - Institute (Box 27, Folder 156)
  - Invitations (Box 27, Folder 157)
  - Invitations (Box 27, Folder 158)
  - Invitations (Box 27, Folder 159)
  - Invitations (Box 27, Folder 160)
  - Jackson - Jarman (Box 27, Folder 161)
  - Jarvis - Jasper (Box 28, Folder 162)
  - Javits, Jacob (Box 28, Folder 163)
  - Jeffrey - Johns (Box 28, Folder 164)
  - Johnson (Box 28, Folder 165)
  - Johnson (Box 28, Folder 166)
  - Johnson - Jondahl (Box 28, Folder 167)
  - Jones (Box 29, Folder 168)
  - Jones (Box 29, Folder 169)
  - Jordan - Jurgemeyer (Box 29, Folder 170)
  - J General (Box 29, Folder 0170A)
  - Kachlein - Katz (Box 29, Folder 171)
  - Katzen - Kaye (Box 29, Folder 172)
  - Kean - Keebler (Box 29, Folder 173)
  - Keefe - Kelman (Box 29, Folder 174)
  - Kelso, Louis (Box 30, Folder 175)
  - Kelton - Kendall (Box 30, Folder 176)
  - Kennedy (Box 30, Folder 177)